Texts

There are no references to War and Peace in this song. The prologue introduces all of the characters, as well as the events leading up to Book Eight.

Prologue

Featured Characters: ALL, PIERRE, NATASHA, SONYA, MARYA D, ANATOLE, HÉLÈNE, DOLOKHOV, MARY, BOLKONSKY

[PIERRE]
There’s a war going on
Out there somewhere
And Andrey isn’t here
There’s a war going on
Out there somewhere
And Andrey isn’t here

[ALL]
There’s a war going on
Out there somewhere
And Andrey isn’t here
There’s a war going on
Out there somewhere
And Andrey isn’t here

[ALL]
And this is all in your program
You are at the opera
Gonna have to study up a little bit
If you wanna keep with the plot
'Cause it’s a complicated Russian novel
Everyone’s got nine different names
So look it up in your program
We’d appreciate it, thanks a lot
Da da da
Da da da
Da da da...
Natasha!

[NATASHA]
Natasha is young
She loves Andrey with all her heart

[ALL]
She loves Andrey with all her heart
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[SONYA]
Sonya is good
Natasha’s cousin and closest friend

[ALL]
Natasha’s cousin and closest friend
Sonya is good
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[MARYA D]
Marya is old-school, a grande dame of Moscow
Natasha’s godmother, strict yet kind

[ALL]
Natasha’s godmother, strict yet kind
Marya is old-school
Sonya is good
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[ALL]
And this is all in your program
You are at the opera
Gonna have to study up a little bit
If you wanna keep with the plot
'Cause it’s a complicated Russian novel
Everyone’s got nine different names
So look it up in your program
We’d appreciate it, thanks a lot
Da da da
Da da da
Da da da...
Anatole!

[ANATOLE]
Anatole is hot
He spends his money on women and wine

[ALL]
He spends his money on women and wine
Anatole is hot
Marya is old-school
Sonya is good
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[HÉLÈNE]
Hélène is a slut
Anatole’s sister, married to Pierre

[ALL]
Anatole’s sister, married to Pierre
Hélène is a slut
Anatole is hot
Marya is old-school
Sonya is good
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[DOLOKHOV]
Dolokhov is fierce, but not too important
Anatole’s friend, a crazy good shot

[ALL]
Anatole’s friend, a crazy good shot
Dolokhov is fierce
Hélène is a slut
Anatole is hot
Marya is old-school
Sonya is good
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[ALL]
Chandeliers and caviar, the war can’t touch us here
Minor characters!

[BOLKONSKY]
Old Prince Bolkonsky is crazy

[MARY]
And Mary is plain

[MARY, BOLKONSKY]
Andrey’s family, totally messed up

[BALAGA]
And Balaga’s just for fun!

[ALL]
Balaga’s just for fun!
Balaga is fun
Bolkonsky is crazy
Mary is plain
Dolokhov is fierce
Hélène is a slut
Anatole is hot
Marya is old-school
Sonya is good
Natasha is young
And Andrey isn’t here

[ALL]
And what about Pierre?
Dear, bewildered and awkward Pierre?
What about Pierre?
Rich, unhappily married Pierre?
What about Pierre?
What about Pierre?
What about Pierre?

Texts

Book 8 References

All take glasses; you too, Balagá. Well, comrades and friends of my youth, we’ve had our fling and lived and reveled. Eh? And now, when shall we meet again? I am going abroad. We have had a good time—now farewell, lads! To our health! Hurrah!... he cried, and emptying his glass flung it on the floor.

No, stop! said Anatole. Shut the door; we have first to sit down. That’s the way.

And where’s the fur cloak? asked Dólokhov. Hey, Ignátka! Go to Matrëna Matrévna and ask her for the sable cloak. I have heard what elopements are like, continued Dólokhov with a wink. Why, she’ll rush out more dead than alive just in the things she is wearing; if you delay at all there’ll be tears and Papa and Mamma, and she’s frozen in a minute and must go back—but you wrap the fur cloak round her first thing and carry her to the sleigh.

That’s the way, said Dólokhov

Well, good-by, Matrëna, said Anatole, kissing her. Ah, my revels here are over. Remember me to Stëshka. There, good-by! Good-by, Matrëna, wish me luck!

Go! he cried, twisting the reins round his hands, and the troyka tore down the Nikítski Boulevard.

When they reached the gate Dólokhov whistled. The whistle was answered, and a maidservant ran out. Come into the courtyard or you’ll be seen; she’ll come out directly, said she. Dólokhov stayed by the gate. Anatole followed the maid into the courtyard, turned the corner, and ran up into the porch.

Kurágin! Come back! shouted Dólokhov. Betrayed! Back!

The Abduction

Featured Characters: ANATOLE, ALL, PIERRE, DOLOKHOV, BALAGA, MAIDSERVANT, MARYA D

[ANATOLE]
Everyone raise a glass! Whoa...

[ANATOLE]
Well, comrades
We’ve had our fun
Lived, laughed and loved
Friends of my youth
When shall we meet again?
I’m going abroad

[ANATOLE]
Goodbye my Gypsy lovers
All my revels here are over
Well, goodbye, Matryosha
Kiss me one last time, whoa
Remember me to Steshka
There, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye
Wish me luck my Gypsy lovers
Now goodbye, goodbye, goodbye

[ALL]
Goodbye my Gypsy lovers
All my revels here are over
Well, goodbye, Matryosha
Kiss me one last time, whoa
Remember me to Steshka
There, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye
Wish me luck my Gypsy lovers
Now goodbye, goodbye, goodbye

[ANATOLE]
Now drink!

[ALL]
Hurrah!
Smash the glasses on the floor!

They dance.

[ALL]
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!

They dance more. Pierre drunkenly raises a glass.

[ALL]
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!

[PIERRE]
Whoa!

[PIERRE]
Here’s to happiness, freedom, and life!
May your travel be swift as a scythe cuts through the grass!

[ALL]
Whoa...
Whoa...

[PIERRE]
May your sorrows be counted and numbered as many
As drops of wine and vodka that stay in my glass!

[ALL]
Whoa...
Whoa...

[PIERRE]
Vsego horoshego
Na pososhok
Poekhali

[ALL]
Vsego horoshego
Na pososhok
Poekhali
Vsego horoshego
Na pososhok
Poekhali

[ALL]
Vsego horoshego
Na pososhok
Poekhali
Na pososhok!
Poekhali!

[ALL]
Come on, let’s go!...

They start to leave.

[ANATOLE]
Wait, wait, wait!
Shut the door!
First we have to sit down!
Yes, that’s the way

[ANATOLE]
It’s a Russian custom

They shut the door and all sit down for a moment.

[ANATOLE]
All right

They start to leave.

[DOLOKHOV]
Wait, wait, wait, wait!
Where’s the fur cloak?
Huh?

[DOLOKHOV]
I have heard what elopements are like
She’ll rush out more dead than alive
Just in the things she is wearing
If you delay at all, there’ll be tears and “Papa” and “Mama”
And she’s frozen in a minute and must go back

[DOLOKHOV]
But you wrap the fur cloak 'round her
And you carry her to the sleigh
That’s the way
That’s the way

[ALL]
That’s the way
That’s the way

[BALAGA]
Let’s get outta here!

[BALAGA]
And the troika tore down Nikitski Boulevard
Whoa! Giddyup, now! Whoa! Whoa!

[ALL]
Hey Balaga
Ho Balaga
Hey hey ho Balaga
Hey hey Balaga
The famous troika driver

[ALL]
Hey Balaga
Ho Balaga
Hey hey hey Balaga
Hey hey Balaga
The famous troika driver

[DOLOKHOV]
When they reached the gate Dolokhov whistled
The whistle was answered, and a maidservant ran out

[MAIDSERVANT]
Come in through the courtyard or you’ll be seen; she’ll come out directly

[DOLOKHOV]
Dolokhov stayed by the gate
Anatole followed the maid into the courtyard
Turned the corner, ran up to the porch

Anatole is stopped by Marya D.

[MARYA D]
You will not enter my house, scoundrel!

[DOLOKHOV]
Anatole, come back!
Betrayed! Betrayed!
Betrayed, Anatole! Betrayed!
Come back!
Betrayed, Anatole! Betrayed! Betrayed!

Dolokhov rushes in and rescues Anatole. They flee.

Texts

Book 8 References

You know, I adore little girls, they lose their heads at once, pursued Anatole.

Anatole was at the door, evidently on the lookout for the Rostóvs.

As soon as she saw him she was seized by the same feeling she had had at the opera—gratified vanity at his admiration of her and fear at the absence of a moral barrier between them.

Adorable! divine! delicious! was heard from every side. Natásha looked at the fat actress, but neither saw nor heard nor understood anything of what went on before her. She only felt herself again completely borne away into this strange senseless world—so remote from her old world—a world in which it was impossible to know what was good or bad, reasonable or senseless. Behind her sat Anatole, and conscious of his proximity she experienced a frightened sense of expectancy.

He said this at a moment when she alone could hear him. You are enchanting... from the moment I saw you I have never ceased...

Anatole asked Natásha for a valse and as they danced he pressed her waist and hand and told her she was bewitching and that he loved her. During the écossaise, which she also danced with him, Anatole said nothing when they happened to be by themselves, but merely gazed at her. Natásha lifted her frightened eyes to him, but there was such confident tenderness in his affectionate look and smile that she could not, whilst looking at him, say what she had to say. She lowered her eyes.

Don’t say such things to me. I am betrothed and love another, she said rapidly.... She glanced at him.

Don’t speak to me of that! What can I do? said he. I tell you I am madly, madly, in love with you! Is it my fault that you are enchanting?... It’s our turn to begin.

Natásha, animated and excited, looked about her with wide-open frightened eyes and seemed merrier than usual. She understood hardly anything that went on that evening. They danced the écossaise and the Grossvater.

I cannot come to visit you but is it possible that I shall never see you? I love you madly. Can I never...? and, blocking her path, he brought his face close to hers. His large, glittering, masculine eyes were so close to hers that she saw nothing but them. Natalie? he whispered inquiringly while she felt her hands being painfully pressed. Natalie? I don’t understand. I have nothing to say, her eyes replied.

Burning lips were pressed to hers, and at the same instant she felt herself released, and Hélène’s footsteps and the rustle of her dress were heard in the room. Natásha looked round at her, and then, red and trembling, threw a frightened look of inquiry at Anatole and moved toward the door.

She paused. She so wanted a word from him that would explain to her what had happened and to which she could find no answer.

After reaching home Natásha did not sleep all night. She was tormented by the insoluble question whether she loved Anatole or Prince Andrew. She loved Prince Andrew—she remembered distinctly how deeply she loved him. But she also loved Anatole, of that there was no doubt. Else how could all this have happened? thought she. If, after that, I could return his smile when saying good-by, if I was able to let it come to that, it means that I loved him from the first. It means that he is kind, noble, and splendid, and I could not help loving him.

The Ball

Featured Characters: ANATOLE, NATASHA

[ANATOLE]
Waiting at the door
Waiting at the door, waiting
Waiting at the door
Waiting at the door, waiting
Oh, how I adore little girls
They lose their heads at once!

The ball begins; they dance.

[NATASHA]
I am seized by feelings of vanity and fear
There is no barrier between us
Whispers and moans, and ringing in my ear
There is no barrier between us

[NATASHA]
Divine, delicious, but I do not see or hear anything
I'm borne away to a senseless world
So strange, so remote
I don't know good from bad
Anatole
Anatole
I'm so frightened

[ANATOLE]
You are enchanting

[NATASHA]
And as we danced
He pressed my waist and hand
And told me I was

[NATASHA, ANATOLE]
Bewitching

[ANATOLE]
And I love you

[NATASHA, ANATOLE]
Bewitching

[ANATOLE]
And I love you

[NATASHA]
And during the ecossaise, he

[NATASHA, ANATOLE]
Gazed/(Gaze) in my eyes

[NATASHA]
And said nothing, just

[NATASHA, ANATOLE]
Gazed/(Gaze) in my eyes

[NATASHA]
My frightened eyes
Such confident tenderness
I could not say what I had to say

[ANATOLE]
Don't lower your eyes
I love you
I am in love, dear
I am in love
Gaze in my eyes
I love you
You are bewitching
What can I do
Darling, what can I do?

[NATASHA]
Don't say such things
I am betrothed
I love another

[ANATOLE]
Don't speak to me of that!
When I tell you that I am madly, madly in love with you!
Is it my fault that you're enchanting?

[NATASHA]
I'm so frightened
I don't understand anything tonight

[ANATOLE]
I'm here now

Natasha breaks away.

[ANATOLE]
Natalie!

[NATASHA]
I can feel your eyes upon me

[ANATOLE]
Blocking her path, I bring her face close to mine

[NATASHA]
His large, glittering, masculine eyes are so close to mine
That I see nothing else

[ANATOLE]
Is it possible that I should never see you again?
I love you madly!
Can I never?
Natalie?

[NATASHA]
You press my arm

[ANATOLE]
Natalie?

[NATASHA]
You're hurting my hands!

[ANATOLE]
Natalie?

[NATASHA]
I don't understand
I have nothing to say

They kiss.

[NATASHA]
Burning lips pressed to mine
Tell me what just happened
I'm trembling
So frightening
Andrey
But I love you
Of that there is no doubt
How else could all of this have happened?
How else could we have kissed?
It means that I have loved you from the first
It means that you are kind
Noble and splendid
And I could not help loving you
I will love you, Anatole
I'll do anything for you

[NATASHA, ANATOLE]
I'll do anything for you

Texts

Book 8 References

When he returned to Moscow Pierre was handed a letter from Márya Dmítrievna asking him to come and see her on a matter of great importance relating to Andrew Bolkónski and his betrothed.

What can have happened? And what can they want with me? thought he as he dressed to go to Márya Dmítrievna’s.

Márya Dmítrievna informed him that Natásha had refused Prince Andrew without her parents’ knowledge and that the cause of this was Anatole Kurágin into whose society Pierre’s wife had thrown her and with whom Natásha had tried to elope during her father’s absence, in order to be married secretly.

Pierre raised his shoulders and listened open-mouthed to what was told him, scarcely able to believe his own ears. That Prince Andrew’s deeply loved affianced wife—the same Natásha Rostóva who used to be so charming—should give up Bolkónski for that fool Anatole who was already secretly married (as Pierre knew), and should be so in love with him as to agree to run away with him, was something Pierre could not conceive and could not imagine.

They are all alike! he said to himself, reflecting that he was not the only man unfortunate enough to be tied to a bad woman. But still he pitied Prince Andrew to the point of tears and sympathized with his wounded pride, and the more he pitied his friend the more did he think with contempt and even with disgust of that Natásha who had just passed him in the ballroom with such a look of cold dignity.

Natásha looked from one to the other as a hunted and wounded animal looks at the approaching dogs and sportsmen.

She was afraid that the count or Bolkónski, who might arrive at any moment, if they knew of this affair (which she hoped to hide from them) might challenge Anatole to a duel, and she therefore asked Pierre to tell his brother-in-law in her name to leave Moscow and not dare to let her set eyes on him again. Pierre—only now realizing the danger to the old count, Nicholas, and Prince Andrew—promised to do as she wished.

A Call To Pierre

Featured Characters: PIERRE, SERVANT, MARYA D

A servant hands a letter to Pierre.

[SERVANT]
A letter from Marya Dmitryevna asking you to come and visit her
On a matter of great importance
Relating to Andrey Bolkonsky and his betrothed

[PIERRE]
What?
What can they want with me?

He arrives at Marya D.’s.

[MARYA D]
Pierre, old friend I’m sorry it’s late
I’m sorry I haven’t seen you about
Where have you been?
Where have you been?

[PIERRE]
I have been studying

[MARYA D]
Pierre old friend, we need your help
Pierre old friend: the family name!
We need your help
We need your help
There’s ruin at the door

[PIERRE]
Marya?

[MARYA D]
Natasha has let down the family

[PIERRE]
What?

[MARYA D]
Natasha has broken with Andrey

[PIERRE]
What?

[MARYA D]
Natasha has tried to elope

[PIERRE]
What?

[MARYA D]
Natasha and Anatole Kuragin!

[PIERRE]
What?!

[MARYA D]
We need your help
We need your help
There’s ruin at the door

[PIERRE]
Natasha, that charming girl?
I can’t believe my ears
So I am not the only man
Chained to a bad woman
And Anatole, that stupid child
They’ll lock him up for years
For Anatole is a married man!

[MARYA D]
Married? He’s married?

[PIERRE]
Yes

[MARYA D]
Oh wait ’til I tell her

[PIERRE]
Poor Andrey

[MARYA D]
And when Andrey comes home
He will challenge Anatole to a duel
And get himself killed
And all will be ruined

[MARYA D]
You must go see your brother-in-law
And tell him that he must leave Moscow
And not dare to let me set my eyes on him again

[PIERRE]
At once

Texts

Book 8 References

How is it you’re not ashamed to bury such pearls in the country?

Countess Bezúkhova quite deserved her reputation of being a fascinating woman. She could say what she did not think—especially what was flattering—quite simply and naturally.

Oh, my enchantress! she cried to the blushing Natásha. Charming! No, this is really beyond anything, my dear count, said she to Count Rostóv who had followed her in. How can you live in Moscow and go nowhere?

She looked at Natásha’s dresses and praised them, as well as a new dress of her own made of metallic gauze, which she had received from Paris, and advised Natásha to have one like it.

But anything suits you, my charmer! she remarked.

The idea of throwing her brother and Natásha together amused her.

My brother dined with me yesterday—we nearly died of laughter—he ate nothing and kept sighing for you, my charmer! He is madly, quite madly, in love with you, my dear.

How she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty! said Hélène. You must certainly come. If you love somebody, my charmer, that is not a reason to shut yourself up. Even if you are engaged, I am sure your fiancé would wish you to go into society rather than be bored to death.

So she knows I am engaged, and she and her husband Pierre—that good Pierre—have talked and laughed about this. So it’s all right. And again, under Hélène’s influence, what had seemed terrible now seemed simple and natural. And she is such a grande dame, so kind, and evidently likes me so much. And why not enjoy myself? thought Natásha, gazing at Hélène with wide-open, wondering eyes.

Charming

Featured Characters: HÉLÈNE, NATASHA

[HÉLÈNE]
Oh my enchantress
Oh you beautiful thing
Charming, charming
Oh, this is really beyond anything
These dresses suit you
This one, “metallic gauze”
Straight from Paris
Anything suits you, my charmer

[HÉLÈNE]
Oh how she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!!
Oh how she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!!
Charmante, charmante!
You are such a lovely thing
Oh where have you been?
It’s such a shame to bury pearls in the country
Charmante, charmante, charming

[HÉLÈNE]
Now if you have a dress
You must wear it out
How can you live in Moscow and not go nowhere?
So you love somebody, charming
But that’s no reason to shut yourself in
Even if you’re engaged
You must wear your dress out somewhere

[HÉLÈNE]
My brother dined with me yesterday
But he didn’t eat a thing
Cuz he was thinking ’bout you
He kept sighing about you

[HÉLÈNE]
Oh how she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!!
Oh how she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!!
Charmante, charmante!
You are such a lovely thing
Oh where have you been?
It’s such a shame to bury pearls in the country
Charmante, charmante, charming

[HÉLÈNE]
Now a woman with a dress
Is a frightening and powerful thing
You are not a child
When you’re draped in scarlet and lace
Your fiancé would want you to have fun
Rather than be bored to death
Alliez dans le monde
Plutôt que de dépérir d’ennui!

[HÉLÈNE]
My brother is quite madly in love
He is quite madly in love with you, my dear

[HÉLÈNE]
Oh how she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!!
Oh how she blushes, how she blushes, my pretty!!
Charmante, charmante!
You are such a lovely thing
Oh where have you been?
It’s such a shame to bury pearls in the country
Charmante, charmante, charming
Such a shame to bury pearls in the country
Charmante, charmante, charming

[NATASHA]
What once seemed so terrible
Now seems simple and natural
She knows that I’m engaged
And still she talks so frankly
So it must be all right!

[HÉLÈNE]
There is a ball at my house tonight
You must come
Oh your wide-open, wondering eyes!
You will be the prettiest there!
How the thought of throwing them together amuses me!
You must come

[NATASHA]
I will come

Texts

Book 4 References

Such a storm of feelings, thoughts, and memories suddenly arose within him that he could not fall asleep, nor even remain in one place, but had to jump up and pace the room with rapid steps.

Book 2 References

You see, my fwiend, he said, we sleep when we don’t love. We are childwen of the dust... but one falls in love and one is a God, one is pua’ as on the fihst day of cweation... Who’s that now? Send him to the devil, I’m busy! he shouted to Lavrúshka, who went up to him not in the least abashed.

Dust and Ashes

Featured Characters: PIERRE

[PIERRE]
Is this how I die?
Ridiculed and laughed at
Wearing clown shoes
Is this how I die?
Furious and reckless
Sick with booze

[PIERRE]
How did I live?
I taste every wasted minute
Every time I turned away
From the things that might have healed me
How long have I been sleeping?
Is this how I die?
Frightened like a child
Lazy and numb
Is this how I die?
Pretending and preposterous
And dumb

[PIERRE]
How did I live?
Was I kind enough and good enough?
Did I love enough?
Did I ever look up
And see the moon
And the stars
And the sky?
Oh why have I been sleeping?

[PIERRE]
They say we are asleep
Until we fall in love
We are children of dust and ashes
But when we fall in love we wake up
And we are a God
And angels weep
But if I die here tonight
I die in my sleep

[PIERRE]
All of my life I spent searching the words
Of poets and saints and prophets and kings
And now at the end all I know that I’ve learned
Is that all that I know is I don’t know a thing

[PIERRE]
So easy to close off
Place the blame outside
Hiding in my room at night
So terrified
All the things I could have been
But I never had the nerve
Life and love
I don’t deserve

[PIERRE]
So all right, all right
I’ve had my time
Close my eyes
Let the death bells chime
Bury me in burgundy
I just don’t care
Nothing’s left
I looked everywhere

[PIERRE]
Is this how I die?
Was there ever any other way my life could be?
Is this how I die?
Such a storm of feelings inside of me?

[PIERRE]
But then why am I screaming?
Why am I shaking?
Oh God, was there something that I missed?
Did I squander my divinity?
Was happiness within me the whole time?
They say we are asleep
Until we fall in love
We are children of dust and ashes
But when we fall in love we wake up
And we are a God
And angels weep
But if I die here tonight
I die in my sleep

[PIERRE]
They say we are asleep
Until we fall in love
And I’m so ready
To wake up now

[PIERRE]
I want to wake up
Don’t let me die while I’m like this
I want to wake up
God don’t let me die while I’m like this
Please let me wake up now
God don’t let me die while I’m like this
I’m ready
I’m ready
To wake up

Texts

Book 8 References

He drove through the town seeking Anatole Kurágin, at the thought of whom now the blood rushed to his heart and he felt a difficulty in breathing. He was not at the ice hills, nor at the gypsies’, nor at Komoneno’s. Pierre drove to the Club. In the Club all was going on as usual. The members who were assembling for dinner were sitting about in groups; they greeted Pierre and spoke of the town news.

One of Pierre’s acquaintances, while they were talking about the weather, asked if he had heard of Kurágin’s abduction of Rostóva which was talked of in the town, and was it true? Pierre laughed and said it was nonsense for he had just come from the Rostóvs’.

It seemed to him essential to see Natásha. In the evening he drove to his sister’s to discuss with her how to arrange a meeting. When Pierre returned home after vainly hunting all over Moscow, his valet informed him that Prince Anatole was with the countess.

Pierre without greeting his wife whom he had not seen since his return—at that moment she was more repulsive to him than ever—entered the drawing room and seeing Anatole went up to him.

Ah, Pierre, said the countess going up to her husband. You don’t know what a plight our Anatole...

Where you are, there is vice and evil! said Pierre to his wife. Anatole, come with me! I must speak to you, he added in French.

Anatole followed him with his usual jaunty step but his face betrayed anxiety.

Having entered his study Pierre closed the door and addressed Anatole without looking at him.

Find Anatole

Featured Characters: PIERRE, ALL, ANATOLE, HÉLÈNE, SERVANT, NATASHA

[PIERRE]
Anatole, find Anatole
Anatole, find Anatole
The blood rushes to my heart
It’s difficult to breathe
Anatole, find Anatole
Anatole, find Anatole
Not at the ice hills
Not at Matreshka’s
Not at Komoneno’s
Anatole, find Anatole
Anatole, find Anatole
To the Club
And at the Club all is going on as usual
The members eat their dinners
And gossip in small groups

[PIERRE, ALL]
Have I heard of Kuragin’s abduction?
Is it true Natasha is ruined?

[PIERRE]
Nonsense, nonsense
Nothing has happened
Everything is fine

Pierre’s house.

[ANATOLE]
Natasha
Natasha
It is essential that I see Natasha
How can I see her?

[HÉLÈNE]
Anatole, come Anatole
Anatole, hush Anatole

Marya D.’s house.

[NATASHA]
What? What?
I don’t believe that he is married
I don’t believe you
And I stare like a hunted wounded animal
He can’t be married!

Pierre’s house.

[SERVANT]
Good evening sir
Prince Anatole is in the drawing room with the Countess

[HÉLÈNE]
Ah, Pierre
Sweet husband
You don’t know what a plight our Anatole has had

[PIERRE]
Be quiet
I will not greet you
At this moment you are more repulsive to me than ever

[PIERRE]
Anatole, come Anatole
Anatole, must speak to you

[ANATOLE]
Anatole followed with his usual jaunty step
But his face betrayed anxiety

[PIERRE]
Pierre closed the door and addressed Anatole without looking at him

Texts

Book 8 References

Where to? Pierre asked himself. Where can I go now? Surely not to the Club or to pay calls? All men seemed so pitiful, so poor, in comparison with this feeling of tenderness and love he experienced: in comparison with that softened, grateful, last look she had given him through her tears.

It was clear and frosty. Above the dirty, ill-lit streets, above the black roofs, stretched the dark starry sky. Only looking up at the sky did Pierre cease to feel how sordid and humiliating were all mundane things compared with the heights to which his soul had just been raised. At the entrance to the Arbát Square an immense expanse of dark starry sky presented itself to his eyes. Almost in the center of it, above the Prechístenka Boulevard, surrounded and sprinkled on all sides by stars but distinguished from them all by its nearness to the earth, its white light, and its long uplifted tail, shone the enormous and brilliant comet of 1812—the comet which was said to portend all kinds of woes and the end of the world. In Pierre, however, that comet with its long luminous tail aroused no feeling of fear. On the contrary he gazed joyfully, his eyes moist with tears, at this bright comet which, having traveled in its orbit with inconceivable velocity through immeasurable space, seemed suddenly—like an arrow piercing the earth—to remain fixed in a chosen spot, vigorously holding its tail erect, shining and displaying its white light amid countless other scintillating stars. It seemed to Pierre that this comet fully responded to what was passing in his own softened and uplifted soul, now blossoming into a new life.

The Great Comet of 1812

Featured Characters: PIERRE, ALL

[PIERRE]
Where to now?
Where can I go now?
Not to the Club
Not to pay calls

[PIERRE]
Mankind seems so pitiful
So poor
Compared to that softened, grateful, last glance
She gave me through her tears

[ALL]
It was clear and cold
Above the dirty streets
Above the black roofs
Stretched the dark starry sky

[PIERRE]
This vast firmament
Open to my eyes
Wet with tears

[ALL]
And there in the middle
Above Prechistensky Boulevard
Surrounded and sprinkled on all sides by stars
Shines The Great Comet of 1812
The Brilliant Comet of 1812

[PIERRE]
The comet said to portend
Untold horrors
And the end of the world

[PIERRE]
But for me
The comet brings no fear
No, I gaze joyfully

[PIERRE]
And this bright star
Having traced its parabola
With inexpressible speed
Through immeasurable space
Seems suddenly
To have stopped
Like an arrow piercing the earth
Stopped for me

[PIERRE]
It seems to me
That this comet
Feels me
Feels my softened and uplifted soul
And my newly melted heart
Now blossoming
Into a new life

Texts

Book 8 References

Anatole, who was as handsome at close quarters as at a distance, sat down beside her and told her he had long wished to have this happiness—ever since the Narýshkins’ ball in fact, at which he had had the well-remembered pleasure of seeing her. Kurágin was much more sensible and simple with women than among men. He talked boldly and naturally, and Natásha was strangely and agreeably struck by the fact that there was nothing formidable in this man about whom there was so much talk, but that on the contrary his smile was most naïve, cheerful, and good-natured.

Kurágin asked her opinion of the performance and told her how at a previous performance Semënova had fallen down on the stage.

And do you know, Countess, he said, suddenly addressing her as an old, familiar acquaintance, we are getting up a costume tournament; you ought to take part in it! It will be great fun. We shall all meet at the Karágins’! Please come! No! Really, eh? said he.

While saying this he never removed his smiling eyes from her face, her neck, and her bare arms. Natásha knew for certain that he was enraptured by her. This pleased her, yet his presence made her feel constrained and oppressed. When she was not looking at him she felt that he was looking at her shoulders, and she involuntarily caught his eye so that he should look into hers rather than this. But looking into his eyes she was frightened, realizing that there was not that barrier of modesty she had always felt between herself and other men. She did not know how it was that within five minutes she had come to feel herself terribly near to this man. When she turned away she feared he might seize her from behind by her bare arm and kiss her on the neck. They spoke of most ordinary things, yet she felt that they were closer to one another than she had ever been to any man.

During one of these moments of awkward silence when Anatole’s prominent eyes were gazing calmly and fixedly at her, Natásha, to break the silence, asked him how he liked Moscow.

At first I did not like it much, because what makes a town pleasant ce sont les jolies femmes, * isn’t that so? But now I like it very much indeed, he said, looking at her significantly. You’ll come to the costume tournament, Countess? Do come! and putting out his hand to her bouquet and dropping his voice, he added, You will be the prettiest there. Do come, dear countess, and give me this flower as a pledge!

She smiled just as he was doing, gazing straight into his eyes. And again she felt with horror that no barrier lay between him and her.

Natasha and Anatole

Featured Characters: NATASHA, ANATOLE

[ANATOLE]
I have long wished to have this happiness
Ever since the Naryshkins’ ball
Where I had the well-remembered pleasure of seeing you
How do you like the performance?
Last week Semenova fell down on the stage

[NATASHA]
He is sensible and simple
Bold and natural
So strange and agreeable
There is nothing formidable
His smile is most naive
Cheerful and good-natured
And he’s as handsome up close as at a distance
And he’s as handsome up close as at a distance

[ANATOLE]
And do you know, Natasha
We are having a costume tournament soon
You ought to come, please come!

[NATASHA]
Oh—

[ANATOLE]
You ought to come, please come!

[NATASHA]
Oh, I—

[ANATOLE]
And I never remove my smiling eyes
From your face, your neck, your bare arms
And I never remove my smiling eyes
From your face, your neck, your bare arms

[NATASHA]
I know for certain that he is taken by me
I know for certain that he is enraptured by me
I feel him looking at my shoulders
My face, my neck, my bare arms

[ANATOLE]
And I look you in the eye

[ANATOLE, NATASHA]
And I look you in the eye

[NATASHA]
And looking into his eyes
I am frightened
There’s not that barrier of modesty
I’ve always felt with men
I feel so terribly near
I fear that he may seize me from behind
And kiss me on the neck

[NATASHA]
How do you like Moscow?

[ANATOLE]
At first I did not like it much
Because what makes a town pleasant
Ce sont les jolies femmes
Isn’t that so?
But now I like it very much indeed
Do come to the costume tournament Countess
Do come!
You will be the prettiest there
You will be the prettiest there
Do come, dear Countess, and give me this flower as a pledge
We are speaking of most ordinary things

[NATASHA]
Yet I feel closer to you than I’ve ever felt with any other man
No one else is here
No one else can see us
Your eyes
Your eyes
Your eyes
Oh your eyes

[ANATOLE]
It’s all right, Natasha, I’m here

[ANATOLE, NATASHA]
So near
Nothing between us
Smile at me
There is nothing between us

Texts

Book 8 References

O God, if he were here now I would not behave as I did then, but differently. I would not be silly and afraid of things, I would simply embrace him, cling to him, and make him look at me with those searching inquiring eyes with which he has so often looked at me, and then I would make him laugh as he used to laugh. And his eyes—how I see those eyes! thought Natásha. And what do his father and sister matter to me? I love him alone, him, him, with that face and those eyes, with his smile, manly and yet childlike....

Book 6 References

Sónya! Sónya! he again heard the first speaker. Oh, how can you sleep? Only look how glorious it is! Ah, how glorious! Do wake up, Sónya! she said almost with tears in her voice. There never, never was such a lovely night before!

Do just come and see what a moon!... Oh, how lovely! Come here.... Darling, sweetheart, come here! There, you see? I feel like sitting down on my heels, putting my arms round my knees like this, straining tight, as tight as possible, and flying away! Like this....

Book 7 References

No, I don’t believe we ever were in animals, said Natásha, still in a whisper though the music had ceased. But I am certain that we were angels somewhere there, and have been here, and that is why we remember....

No One Else

Featured Characters: NATASHA

[NATASHA]
The moon—

[NATASHA]
First time I heard your voice
Moonlight burst into the room
And I saw your eyes
And I saw your smile
And the world opened wide
And the world was inside of me

[NATASHA]
And I catch my breath
And I laugh and blush
And I hear guitars
You are so good for me
I love you I love you I love you I love you I love you

[NATASHA]
Oh the moon
Oh the snow in the moonlight
And your childlike eyes
And your distant smile
I’ll never be this happy again
You and I
And no one else

[NATASHA]
We’ve done this all before
We were angels once
Don’t you remember?
Joy and life
Inside our souls
And nobody knows
Just you and me
It’s our secret

[NATASHA]
This winter sky
How can anyone sleep?
There was never such a night before!
I feel like putting my arms round my knees
And squeezing tight as possible
And flying away
Like this...

[NATASHA]
Oh the moon
Oh the snow in the moonlight
And your childlike eyes
And your distant smile
I’ll never be this happy again
You and I
You and I
You and I
And no one else

[NATASHA]
Maybe he’ll come today
Maybe he came already
And he’s sitting in the drawing room
And I simply forgot

Texts

Book 8 References

The music sounded louder and through the door rows of brightly lit boxes in which ladies sat with bare arms and shoulders, and noisy stalls brilliant with uniforms, glittered before their eyes. A lady entering the next box shot a glance of feminine envy at Natásha. The curtain had not yet risen and the overture was being played. Natásha, smoothing her gown, went in with Sónya and sat down, scanning the brilliant tiers of boxes opposite. A sensation she had not experienced for a long time—that of hundreds of eyes looking at her bare arms and neck—suddenly affected her both agreeably and disagreeably and called up a whole crowd of memories, desires and emotions associated with that feeling.

The two remarkably pretty girls, Natásha and Sónya, with Count Rostóv who had not been seen in Moscow for a long time, attracted general attention. Moreover, everybody knew vaguely of Natásha’s engagement to Prince Andrew, and knew that the Rostóvs had lived in the country ever since, and all looked with curiosity at a fiancée who was making one of the best matches in Russia.

Dear me, Michael Kirílovich has grown still stouter! remarked the count. Look at our Anna Mikháylovna—what a headdress she has on!The Karágins, Julie—and Borís with them. One can see at once that they’re engaged....

They are talking about us, about me and him! thought Natásha. And he no doubt is calming her jealousy of me. They needn’t trouble themselves! If only they knew how little I am concerned about any of them.

He stood in full view of the audience, well aware that he was attracting everyone’s attention, yet as much at ease as though he were in his own room. Around him thronged Moscow’s most brilliant young men, whom he evidently dominated.

He did, replied Shinshín. He was in the Caucasus and ran away from there. They say he has been acting as minister to some ruling prince in Persia, where he killed the Shah’s brother. Now all the Moscow ladies are mad about him! It’s Dólokhov the Persian that does it!

A tall, beautiful woman with a mass of plaited hair and much exposed plump white shoulders and neck, round which she wore a double string of large pearls, entered the adjoining box rustling her heavy silk dress and took a long time settling into her place.

Natásha involuntarily gazed at that neck, those shoulders, and pearls and coiffure, and admired the beauty of the shoulders and the pearls. While Natásha was fixing her gaze on her for the second time the lady looked round and, meeting the count’s eyes, nodded to him and smiled. She was the Countess Bezúkhova, Pierre’s wife, and the count, who knew everyone in society, leaned over and spoke to her.

Have you been here long, Countess? he inquired. I’ll call, I’ll call to kiss your hand. I’m here on business and have brought my girls with me. They say Semënova acts marvelously. Count Pierre never used to forget us. Is he here?

As soon as it rose everyone in the boxes and stalls became silent, and all the men, old and young, in uniform and evening dress, and all the women with gems on their bare flesh, turned their whole attention with eager curiosity to the stage.

After her life in the country, and in her present serious mood, all this seemed grotesque and amazing to Natásha. She could not follow the opera nor even listen to the music; she saw only the painted cardboard and the queerly dressed men and women who moved, spoke, and sang so strangely in that brilliant light. She knew what it was all meant to represent, but it was so pretentiously false and unnatural that she first felt ashamed for the actors and then amused at them. She looked at the faces of the audience, seeking in them the same sense of ridicule and perplexity she herself experienced, but they all seemed attentive to what was happening on the stage, and expressed delight which to Natásha seemed feigned.

especially at Hélène in the next box, who—apparently quite unclothed—sat with a quiet tranquil smile

And feeling the bright light that flooded the whole place and the warm air heated by the crowd, Natásha little by little began to pass into a state of intoxication she had not experienced for a long while.

As she looked and thought, the strangest fancies unexpectedly and disconnectedly passed through her mind: the idea occurred to her of jumping onto the edge of the box and singing the aria the actress was singing, then she wished to touch with her fan an old gentleman sitting not far from her, then to lean over to Hélène and tickle her.

At a moment when all was quiet before the commencement of a song, a door leading to the stalls on the side nearest the Rostóvs’ box creaked, and the steps of a belated arrival were heard. There’s Kurágin! whispered Shinshín. Countess Bezúkhova turned smiling to the newcomer, and Natásha, following the direction of that look, saw an exceptionally handsome adjutant approaching their box with a self-assured yet courteous bearing. This was Anatole Kurágin whom she had seen and noticed long ago at the ball in Petersburg. He was now in an adjutant’s uniform with one epaulet and a shoulder knot. He moved with a restrained swagger which would have been ridiculous had he not been so good-looking and had his handsome face not worn such an expression of good-humored complacency and gaiety. Though the performance was proceeding, he walked deliberately down the carpeted gangway, his sword and spurs slightly jingling and his handsome perfumed head held high. Having looked at Natásha he approached his sister, laid his well gloved hand on the edge of her box, nodded to her, and leaning forward asked a question, with a motion toward Natásha.

Mais charmante! said he, evidently referring to Natásha, who did not exactly hear his words but understood them from the movement of his lips. Then he took his place in the first row of the stalls and sat down beside Dólokhov, nudging with his elbow in a friendly and offhand way that Dólokhov whom others treated so fawningly. He winked at him gaily, smiled, and rested his foot against the orchestra screen.

She turned and their eyes met. Almost smiling, he gazed straight into her eyes with such an enraptured caressing look that it seemed strange to be so near him, to look at him like that, to be so sure he admired her, and not to be acquainted with him.

In the second act there was scenery representing tombstones, there was a round hole in the canvas to represent the moon, shades were raised over the footlights, and from horns and contrabass came deep notes while many people appeared from right and left wearing black cloaks and holding things like daggers in their hands. They began waving their arms.

The scene of the third act represented a palace in which many candles were burning and pictures of knights with short beards hung on the walls. In the middle stood what were probably a king and a queen. The king waved his right arm and, evidently nervous, sang something badly and sat down on a crimson throne.

But suddenly a storm came on, chromatic scales and diminished sevenths were heard in the orchestra, everyone ran off, again dragging one of their number away, and the curtain dropped. Once more there was a terrible noise and clatter among the audience, and with rapturous faces everyone began shouting: Duport! Duport! Duport!

During the entr’acte a whiff of cold air came into Hélène’s box, the door opened, and Anatole entered, stooping and trying not to brush against anyone.

The Opera

Featured Characters: MARYA D, SONYA, ANATOLE, HÉLÈNE, ALL, NATASHA, SERVANT

[MARYA D]
The opera, the opera!
Stop mooning and moaning, we’ll miss the curtain!

[SERVANT]
Ladies
Welcome to the opera

[SONYA]
Bare arms and shoulders
Brilliant uniforms
Pearls and silk
Glittering before our eyes
Feminine envy
A whole crowd of memories
Desires and emotions
Natasha, smooth your gown

[ALL]
Natasha, smooth your gown

[NATASHA]
Looking in the glass
I see I am pretty
Not a girl anymore
I’ve never felt like this before
Hundreds of eyes
Looking at my bare arms
My bare arms and neck
My bare arms and shoulders

[ALL]
The two remarkably pretty girls
Had not been seen in Moscow in many years
Everybody knew vaguely of Natasha’s engagement
One of the finest matches in all of Russia

[SONYA]
Look, there’s Alexey, home from the war at last

[MARYA D]
He has changed
Dear me, Michael Kirilovich has grown still stouter!

[ALL]
There’s Boris and Julie, engaged
And Anna Mikhaylovna, what a headdress she has on!

[HÉLÈNE]
And is that Natasha

[ALL]
And is that Natasha
And is that Natasha

[NATASHA]
They are looking at me
They are talking about me!
They all like me so much
The women envious
The men calming their jealousy

[SERVANT]
Announcing Fedya Dolokhov
He dominates Moscow’s most brilliant young men
He stands in full view
Well aware he’s attracting attention
Yet as much at ease as though he were in his own room

[MARYA D]
Dolokhov was in the Caucasus
And he killed the Shah’s brother!
Now all the Moscow ladies are mad about him
Dolokhov the assassin!

[SERVANT]
Announcing Countess Hélène Bezukhova
The queen of society
Beautiful, barely clothed
Plump bare shoulders, and much-exposed neck
Round which she wears a double string of pearls

[ALL]
Hélène and Dolokhov, arm in arm
Pierre the cuckold sits at home
Pierre the cuckold sits at home
The poor man

[PIERRE]
No, I am enjoying myself at home this evening

[NATASHA]
Oh, that neck
Oh, those pearls

[HÉLÈNE]
So beautiful
What a charming young girl
So enchanting

[NATASHA]
I blush scarlet

[MARYA D]
Countess Bezukhova, Pierre’s wife
Have you been here long?
And where is dear Pierre?
He never used to forget us

[NATASHA]
Yes Pierre, that good man
A little sad, a little stout
He must come visit us

[HÉLÈNE]
I will implore him to do so

[MARYA D]
There’s a woman one should stay far away from
Now Natasha
The curtain rises

[ALL]
The curtain rises

[NATASHA]
Everyone in the boxes and the stalls became silent
All the men, old and young, in uniform and evening dress
All the women in the hall
With gems on their bare flesh
Turned their whole attention
With curiosity to the stage

Two singers perform a scene from an avant-garde opera. It is grotesque and amazing.

[NATASHA]
Grotesque and amazing
I cannot follow the opera
Or even listen to the music
I see painted cardboard
Queerly dressed actors
Moving and singing so strangely in the lights
So false and unnatural
I’m ashamed and amused
And everyone else seems oblivious
Yes everyone feigns delight

[SONYA]
And feeling the flood of brilliant lights
The warm perfumed air heated by the crowd
Natasha little by little
Began to pass into a state of intoxication

[NATASHA]
Oh I’d tickle you all if I could
Oh I’d tickle you all if I could

[SONYA]
And then
A rush of cold air

[NATASHA, SONYA]
An exceptionally handsome man walked in
With a confident yet courteous air

[HÉLÈNE]
This was Hélène’s brother
Anatole Kuragin
He moved with a swagger
Which would have been ridiculous
Had he not been so good-looking
And though it was the middle of the act
He walked right down the aisle
His sword and spurs jangling
His handsome perfumed head held high
And he looked right at Natasha

[ANATOLE]
Mais charmante

[HÉLÈNE]
And he took his place in the front row next to Dolokhov

[NATASHA]
How handsome he is
How intoxicating

[SONYA]
In the second act there were tombstones
The moon over the footlights
Horns and contrabass
Black cloaks and daggers in their hands

[NATASHA]
I turn around again and our eyes meet
He gazes straight into my eyes
He is talking about me

[SONYA]
Candles burning
A crimson throne
The Tsar wails a mournful tune
They all wave their arms
And everybody cheers
“Bravo, bravo!”

[NATASHA]
Every time I look at him
He’s looking at me
Every time I look at him
He's looking at me
Every time I look at him

[SONYA]
A terrible noise, a clatter in the crowd
A storm of chromatic scales and diminished sevenths
With rapturous faces everyone was shouting
Screaming and shouting, “Bravo!”

[ALL]
Bravo, bravo
Bravo, bravo
Bravo, bravo

[SONYA]
And then
A rush of cold air
And Anatole entered the box

Texts

Book 8 References

You promised Countess Rostóva to marry her and were about to elope with her, is that so?

Mon cher, answered Anatole (their whole conversation was in French), I don’t consider myself bound to answer questions put to me in that tone.

Pierre’s face, already pale, became distorted by fury. He seized Anatole by the collar of his uniform with his big hand and shook him from side to side till Anatole’s face showed a sufficient degree of terror.

When I tell you that I must talk to you!... repeated Pierre. Come now, this is stupid. What? said Anatole, fingering a button of his collar that had been wrenched loose with a bit of the cloth. You’re a scoundrel and a blackguard, and I don’t know what deprives me from the pleasure of smashing your head with this! said Pierre, expressing himself so artificially because he was talking French.

Did you promise to marry her? I... I didn’t think of it. I never promised, because...

Have you any letters of hers? Any letters? he said, moving toward Anatole.

I shan’t be violent, don’t be afraid! said Pierre in answer to a frightened gesture of Anatole’s. First, the letters, said he, as if repeating a lesson to himself. Secondly, he continued after a short pause, again rising and again pacing the room, tomorrow you must get out of Moscow. But how can I?... Thirdly, Pierre continued without listening to him, you must never breathe a word of what has passed between you and Countess Rostóva. I know I can’t prevent your doing so, but if you have a spark of conscience... Pierre paced the room several times in silence. Anatole sat at a table frowning and biting his lips.

After all, you must understand that besides your pleasure there is such a thing as other people’s happiness and peace, and that you are ruining a whole life for the sake of amusing yourself! Amuse yourself with women like my wife—with them you are within your rights, for they know what you want of them. They are armed against you by the same experience of debauchery; but to promise a maid to marry her... to deceive, to kidnap.... Don’t you understand that it is as mean as beating an old man or a child?...

I don’t know about that, eh? said Anatole, growing more confident as Pierre mastered his wrath. I don’t know that and don’t want to, he said, not looking at Pierre and with a slight tremor of his lower jaw, but you have used such words to me—mean and so on—which as a man of honor I can’t allow anyone to use.

Is it satisfaction you want? said Pierre ironically. You could at least take back your words. What? If you want me to do as you wish, eh?

I take them back, I take them back! said Pierre, and I ask you to forgive me. Pierre involuntarily glanced at the loose button. And if you require money for your journey... Anatole smiled. The expression of that base and cringing smile, which Pierre knew so well in his wife, revolted him. Oh, vile and heartless brood! he exclaimed, and left the room. Next day Anatole left for Petersburg.

Pierre and Anatole

Featured Characters: PIERRE, ANATOLE

During this scene, Natasha prepares to poison herself.

[PIERRE]
You promised Countess Rostova to marry her and were about to elope, is that so?

[ANATOLE]
Mon cher
I don’t consider myself bound to answer questions put to me in that tone

[PIERRE]
My face, already pale
Becomes distorted by fury
I seize you by the collar with my big big hands
And I shake you from side to side
Until your face shows a sufficient degree of terror
When I tell you I must talk to you!

[ANATOLE]
Come now, this is stupid!
What what, don’t don’t!

[PIERRE]
You’re a scoundrel and a blackguard
And I don’t know what deprives me of the pleasure
Of smashing your head in with this!

He takes a heavy paperweight and lifts it threateningly, but at once puts it back in its place.

[PIERRE]
Did you promise to marry her?

[ANATOLE]
I didn’t think of it. I never promised, because—

[PIERRE]
Have you any letters of hers?
Any letters?
I shan’t be violent, don’t be afraid

Anatole hands Pierre a pack of letters.

[PIERRE]
First, the letters
Second, tomorrow you must get out of Moscow

[ANATOLE]
But how can I?

[PIERRE]
Third
You must never breathe a word of what has happened between you and the Countess
Now I know I can’t prevent your doing so
But if you have a spark of conscience—
Pierre paces the room several times in silence

[ANATOLE]
Anatole sits at a table frowning and biting his lips

[PIERRE]
After all, you must understand
That besides your pleasure
There is such a thing as other people
And their happiness and peace
And that you are ruining a whole life
For the sake of amusing yourself!
Amuse yourself with women like my wife
With them you’re within your rights
But to promise a young girl to marry her
To deceive, to kidnap
Don’t you understand that that’s as cruel
As beating an old man or a child?

[ANATOLE]
Well, I don’t know about that, eh?
I don’t know that and I don’t want to
But you have used such words to me
“Scoundrel” and so on
Which as a man of honor
I will not allow anyone to use

[PIERRE]
Is it satisfaction you want?

[ANATOLE]
You could at least take back your words, eh?
If you want me to do as you wish?

Natasha drinks the poison.

[PIERRE]
Fine, I take them back, I take them back!
And I ask you to forgive me
And if you require money for your journey—

[ANATOLE]
Anatole smiled
The reflection of that base and cringing smile
Which Pierre knew so well in his wife
Revolted him

[PIERRE]
Oh, vile and heartless brood!

[ANATOLE]
Next day Anatole left
For Petersburg!

Texts

Book 8 References

Well, how are you? Still getting stouter? he said with animation, but the new wrinkle on his forehead deepened. Yes, I am well, he said in answer to Pierre’s question, and smiled.

Forgive me for troubling you....

I have received a refusal from Countess Rostóva and have heard reports of your brother-in-law having sought her hand, or something of that kind. Is that true?

Here are her letters and her portrait, said he. He took the packet from the table and handed it to Pierre. Give this to the countess... if you see her. She is very ill, said Pierre.

He left long ago. She has been at death’s door. I much regret her illness, said Prince Andrew; and he smiled like his father, coldly, maliciously, and unpleasantly.

Well, it doesn’t matter, said Prince Andrew. Tell Countess Rostóva that she was and is perfectly free and that I wish her all that is good. Pierre took the packet. Prince Andrew, as if trying to remember whether he had something more to say, or waiting to see if Pierre would say anything, looked fixedly at him. I say, do you remember our discussion in Petersburg? asked Pierre, about... Yes, returned Prince Andrew hastily. I said that a fallen woman should be forgiven, but I didn’t say I could forgive her. I can’t.

Prince Andrew interrupted him and cried sharply: Yes, ask her hand again, be magnanimous, and so on?... Yes, that would be very noble, but I am unable to follow in that gentleman’s footsteps. If you wish to be my friend never speak to me of that... of all that! Well, good-by. So you’ll give her the packet?

Pierre and Andrey

Featured Characters: PIERRE, ANDREY

Andrey visits Pierre.

[ANDREY]
Well, how are you?
Still getting stouter?

[PIERRE]
There’s a new wrinkle
On your forehead old friend

[ANDREY]
It’s good to see you
I’ve been away too long

[PIERRE]
My friend, you are in need
Your face is gloomy

[ANDREY]
No, I am well
There’s a war going on

[ANDREY]
Forgive me for troubling you
I have received a refusal from Countess Rostova
And have heard reports of your brother-in-law having sought her hand
Or something of that kind
Is this true?

[PIERRE]
Something of that kind

[ANDREY]
Here are her letters
Please give them to the Countess

[PIERRE]
Natasha is ill
She has been at death’s door

[ANDREY]
I much regret her illness

[PIERRE]
And he smiled like his father
Coldly, maliciously

[ANDREY]
Well, it doesn’t matter

[PIERRE]
You told me once
A fallen woman should be forgiven

[ANDREY]
But I didn’t say that I could forgive
I can’t

[ANDREY]
Yes, ask her hand again
Be magnanimous, and so on
Yes, that would be very noble
But I can’t be that man
If you wish to be my friend
Never speak of that again

[ANDREY]
Well, goodbye

Pierre takes the letters to Natasha.

Texts

Book 8 References

Natásha was standing in the middle of the drawing room, emaciated, with a pale set face, but not at all shamefaced as Pierre expected to find her. When he appeared at the door she grew flurried, evidently undecided whether to go to meet him or to wait till he came up.

Pierre hastened to her. He thought she would give him her hand as usual; but she, stepping up to him, stopped, breathing heavily, her arms hanging lifelessly just in the pose she used to stand in when she went to the middle of the ballroom to sing, but with quite a different expression of face.

Peter Kirílovich, she began rapidly, Prince Bolkónski was your friend—is your friend, she corrected herself. (It seemed to her that everything that had once been must now be different.) He told me once to apply to you...

Pierre sniffed as he looked at her, but did not speak. Till then he had reproached her in his heart and tried to despise her, but he now felt so sorry for her that there was no room in his soul for reproach.

He is here now: tell him... to for... forgive me! She stopped and breathed still more quickly, but did not shed tears. Yes... I will tell him, answered Pierre; but...

No, I know all is over, she said hurriedly. No, that can never be. I’m only tormented by the wrong I have done him. Tell him only that I beg him to forgive, forgive, forgive me for everything....

I will tell him, I will tell him everything once more, said Pierre. But... I should like to know one thing....

I should like to know, did you love... Pierre did not know how to refer to Anatole and flushed at the thought of him—did you love that bad man? Don’t call him bad! said Natásha. But I don’t know, don’t know at all....

She began to cry and a still greater sense of pity, tenderness, and love welled up in Pierre. He felt the tears trickle under his spectacles and hoped they would not be noticed.

We won’t speak of it any more, my dear, said Pierre, and his gentle, cordial tone suddenly seemed very strange to Natásha. We won’t speak of it, my dear—I’ll tell him everything; but one thing I beg of you, consider me your friend and if you want help, advice, or simply to open your heart to someone—not now, but when your mind is clearer--think of me! He took her hand and kissed it. I shall be happy if it’s in my power...

Pierre grew confused. Don’t speak to me like that. I am not worth it! exclaimed Natásha and turned to leave the room, but Pierre held her hand.

Stop, stop! You have your whole life before you, said he to her. Before me? No! All is over for me, she replied with shame and self-abasement. All over? he repeated. If I were not myself, but the handsomest, cleverest, and best man in the world, and were free, I would this moment ask on my knees for your hand and your love! For the first time for many days Natásha wept tears of gratitude and tenderness, and glancing at Pierre she went out of the room.

Pierre too when she had gone almost ran into the anteroom, restraining tears of tenderness and joy that choked him, and without finding the sleeves of his fur cloak threw it on and got into his sleigh.

Home! said Pierre, and despite twenty-two degrees of frost Fahrenheit he threw open the bearskin cloak from his broad chest and inhaled the air with joy.

Pierre and Natasha

Featured Characters: PIERRE, NATASHA

[PIERRE]
Natasha was standing
In the middle of the drawing room
With a pale yet steady face
When I appeared in the doorway
She grew flustered and I hurried to her
I thought that she would give me her hand
But instead she stopped
Breathing heavily
Her thin arms hanging lifelessly
Just in the very pose
She used to stand in as a young girl
When she went to the middle of the ballroom to sing
But the look on her face was quite different

[NATASHA]
Peter Kirilovich

[PIERRE]
Pierre

[NATASHA]
Prince Bolkonsky was your friend—
He is your friend
He once told me that I should turn to you

[PIERRE]
Pierre sniffed as he looked at her, but he didn’t speak
’Til then he had reproached her, and tried to despise her
But now he felt such pity for her
That there was no room in his soul for reproach

[NATASHA]
He is here now
Tell him to—tell him to forgive me

[PIERRE]
Yes, I will tell him to forgive you
But, he gave me your letters—

[NATASHA]
No, I know that all is over
I know that it never can be
But still I’m tormented by the wrongs I’ve done him
Tell him that I beg him to forgive, forgive
Forgive me for everything

[PIERRE]
Yes I will tell him, tell him everything
But—
But I should like to know one thing
Did you love—
Did you love that bad man?

[NATASHA]
Don’t call him bad
But I don’t know, I don’t know at all

[PIERRE]
She began to cry
And a greater sense of pity, tenderness, and love overflowed Pierre’s heart
He felt the tears begin to trickle underneath his spectacles
And he hoped that no one would see

[PIERRE]
We won’t speak of it anymore
We won’t speak of it, my dear
But one thing I beg of you, consider me your friend
And if you ever need help, or simply to open your heart to someone
Not now, but when your mind is clear
Think of me—
Pierre grew confused

[NATASHA]
Don’t speak to me like that
I am not worth it!

[PIERRE]
Stop, stop, stop!
You have your whole life before you—

[NATASHA]
Before me? No, all is over for me!

[PIERRE]
All over?

Music stops.

[PIERRE]
If I were not myself
But the brightest, handsomest
Best man on earth
And if I were free—
I would get down on my knees this minute
And ask you for your hand
And for your love

Music resumes.

[NATASHA]
And for the first time in many days
I weep tears of gratitude
Tears of tenderness
Tears of thanks
And glancing at Pierre
Oh Pierre
I leave the room smiling

[PIERRE]
And restraining tears of tenderness
Tears of joy which choke me
I throw my fur coat on my shoulders
Unable to find the sleeves
Outside, my great broad chest
Breathes in deep the air with joy
Despite the ten degrees of frost
And I get into my sleigh

Texts

Book 8 References

The plan for Natalie Rostóva’s abduction had been arranged and the preparations made by Dólokhov a few days before, and on the day that Sónya, after listening at Natásha’s door, resolved to safeguard her, it was to have been put into execution. Natásha had promised to come out to Kurágin at the back porch at ten that evening. Kurágin was to put her into a troyka he would have ready and to drive her forty miles to the village of Kámenka, where an unfrocked priest was in readiness to perform a marriage ceremony over them. At Kámenka a relay of horses was to wait which would take them to the Warsaw highroad, and from there they would hasten abroad with post horses.

Anatole had a passport, an order for post horses, ten thousand rubles he had taken from his sister and another ten thousand borrowed with Dólokhov’s help.

Two witnesses for the mock marriage—Khvóstikov, a retired petty official whom Dólokhov made use of in his gambling transactions, and Makárin, a retired hussar, a kindly, weak fellow who had an unbounded affection for Kurágin—were sitting at tea in Dólokhov’s front room.

In his large study, the walls of which were hung to the ceiling with Persian rugs, bearskins, and weapons, sat Dólokhov in a traveling cloak and high boots, at an open desk on which lay an abacus and some bundles of paper money. Anatole, with uniform unbuttoned, walked to and fro from the room where the witnesses were sitting, through the study to the room behind, where his French valet and others were packing the last of his things. Dólokhov was counting the money and noting something down.

Do you know? You’d really better drop it all. There’s still time! Fool, retorted Anatole. Don’t talk nonsense! If you only knew... it’s the devil knows what! No, really, give it up! said Dólokhov. I am speaking seriously. It’s no joke, this plot you’ve hatched. What, teasing again? Go to the devil! Eh? said Anatole, making a grimace. Really it’s no time for your stupid jokes, and he left the room.

You wait a bit, he called after him. I’m not joking, I’m talking sense. Come here, come here! Anatole returned and looked at Dólokhov, trying to give him his attention and evidently submitting to him involuntarily. Now listen to me. I’m telling you this for the last time. Why should I joke about it? Did I hinder you? Who arranged everything for you? Who found the priest and got the passport? Who raised the money? I did it all. Well, thank you for it. Do you think I am not grateful? And Anatole sighed and embraced Dólokhov. I helped you, but all the same I must tell you the truth; it is a dangerous business, and if you think about it—a stupid business. Well, you’ll carry her off—all right! Will they let it stop at that? It will come out that you’re already married. Why, they’ll have you in the criminal court....

Oh, nonsense, nonsense! Anatole ejaculated and again made a grimace. Didn’t I explain to you? What? And Anatole, with the partiality dull-witted people have for any conclusion they have reached by their own reasoning, repeated the argument he had already put to Dólokhov a hundred times. Didn’t I explain to you that I have come to this conclusion: if this marriage is invalid, he went on, crooking one finger, then I have nothing to answer for; but if it is valid, no matter! Abroad no one will know anything about it. Isn’t that so? And don’t talk to me, don’t, don’t.

Go to the devil! cried Anatole and, clutching his hair, left the room, but returned at once and dropped into an armchair in front of Dólokhov with his feet turned under him. It’s the very devil! What? Feel how it beats! He took Dólokhov’s hand and put it on his heart. What a foot, my dear fellow! What a glance! A goddess! he added in French.

Now then! Nearly ready? You’re dawdling! he shouted to the servants.

Anatole lay on the sofa in the study leaning on his elbow and smiling pensively, while his handsome lips muttered tenderly to himself.

Come! Balagá is here.

Yes, indeed, that’s a true sage, thought Pierre. He sees nothing beyond the pleasure of the moment, nothing troubles him and so he is always cheerful, satisfied, and serene. What wouldn’t I give to be like him! he thought enviously.

Preparations

Featured Characters: PIERRE, ANATOLE, DOLOKHOV

Pierre runs into Anatole on the street. Pierre is drunk, Anatole in a hurry.

[PIERRE]
Ah, Anatole! Where are you off to?

[ANATOLE]
Pierre, good man
Tonight I go away, on an adventure
You’ll not be seeing me for some time
I’ve found a new pleasure
And I’m taking her away
I’ll send you a letter from Poland

[PIERRE]
Ha! An elopement!
Fool, you are married already!

[ANATOLE]
Don’t talk to me of that!
I will not deprive myself of this one!
Tonight! I take her tonight!
Lend me fifty rubles?

[PIERRE]
Ah, that's a true sage
Living in the moment
What I wouldn’t give to be like him!

[DOLOKHOV]
The plan for Natalie Rostova’s abduction
Had all been arranged and the preparations made
On the day that Sonya decided to save her
That was the day that the game was to be played

[DOLOKHOV]
Natasha was to be on her back porch at ten
Anatole and his troika would scoop her up and then
They’d ride forty miles to the village of Kamenka
Where an unfrocked priest was to make ’em get wed
Then back into the troika off they’d go
Take the Poland highroad to the wedding bed

[ANATOLE]
Passports, horses, ten thousand rubles I have taken from my sister
And another ten thousand raised with Dolokhov’s help

[DOLOKHOV]
Just Anatole, the two wedding witnesses, and me
An abacus and paper money strewn on the desk
Persian rugs and bearskins hanging grotesque
Anatole was walking with his uniform unbuttoned
Walking to and fro
To and fro
To and fro

[ANATOLE, DOLOKHOV]

[DOLOKHOV]
Now wait!
You better
Just
Give it up now
Why dontcha
While there’s still time!
You’d really better drop it all
Give it up now!
While there’s still time!
Do you know?

[ANATOLE]
What, teasing again?
Fool don’t talk nonsense!
Go to the devil! Eh?
Really this is no time for your stupid jokes

[DOLOKHOV]
I am not joking, I am talking sense
This is serious business, a dangerous business
Come here, come here, come here Anatole!
Why would I joke about it?
Me of all people
Who found the priest, raised the money, got the passports, got the horses?

[ANATOLE]
And well I thank you for it
Do you think I am not grateful?

[DOLOKHOV]
And now you’ll carry her away but will they let it stop there?
You haven’t thought this through or do you just don’t care?
Now listen to me tell it to you one last time
They will take you to the court and convict you for your crime
Already married and you’re playing with a little girl
Don’t you know, don’t you think, don’t you know?

[ANATOLE]
Nonsense, nonsense!
I’m scowling and grimacing
Didn’t I explain it to you, didn’t I, what?

[DOLOKHOV]
And here Anatole
With the stubborn attachment small-minded people have
For conclusions they’ve worked out for themselves
Repeated his argument to me for the hundredth time

[ANATOLE]
If this marriage isn’t valid
Then I’m off the hook
But if it is valid, it really doesn’t matter!
No one abroad is gonna know a thing about it
Isn’t that so now don’t you know?
Don’t talk to me, don’t don’t what what
Ah go to hell now
I’m clutching my hair!
It’s the very devil!
Here, feel how it beats!

He presses Dolokhov’s hand to his heart. A light comes up on Natasha across the room.

[ANATOLE]
Ah ma chere, ma chere
Quel pied, quel regard!
What a foot she has, what a glance!
A goddess!

[ANATOLE]
And my handsome lips
Mutter something tender to myself
It’s time!
It’s time!
Now then! Nearly ready? You’re dawdling!
The driver is here
The driver is here
Balaga is here!

Texts

Book 8 References

How was it I noticed nothing? How could it go so far? Can she have left off loving Prince Andrew? And how could she let Kurágin go to such lengths? He is a deceiver and a villain, that’s plain! What will Nicholas, dear noble Nicholas, do when he hears of it? So this is the meaning of her excited, resolute, unnatural look the day before yesterday, yesterday, and today, thought Sónya. But it can’t be that she loves him! She probably opened the letter without knowing who it was from. Probably she is offended by it. She could not do such a thing!

Natásha! she said, just audibly. Natásha awoke and saw Sónya. Ah, you’re back?

And with the decision and tenderness that often come at the moment of awakening, she embraced her friend, but noticing Sónya’s look of embarrassment, her own face expressed confusion and suspicion.

Sónya, you’ve read that letter? she demanded. Yes, answered Sónya softly. Natásha smiled rapturously. No, Sónya, I can’t any longer! she said. I can’t hide it from you any longer. You know, we love one another! Sónya, darling, he writes... Sónya... Sónya stared open-eyed at Natásha, unable to believe her ears. And Bolkónski? she asked. Ah, Sónya, if you only knew how happy I am! cried Natásha. You don’t know what love is.... But, Natásha, can that be all over? Natásha looked at Sónya with wide-open eyes as if she could not grasp the question. Well, then, are you refusing Prince Andrew? said Sónya. Oh, you don’t understand anything! Don’t talk nonsense, just listen! said Natásha, with momentary vexation. But I can’t believe it, insisted Sónya. I don’t understand. How is it you have loved a man for a whole year and suddenly... Why, you have only seen him three times! Natásha, I don’t believe you, you’re joking! In three days to forget everything and so... Three days? said Natásha. It seems to me I’ve loved him a hundred years. It seems to me that I have never loved anyone before. You can’t understand it.... Sónya, wait a bit, sit here, and Natásha embraced and kissed her. I had heard that it happens like this, and you must have heard it too, but it’s only now that I feel such love. It’s not the same as before. As soon as I saw him I felt he was my master and I his slave, and that I could not help loving him. Yes, his slave! Whatever he orders I shall do. You don’t understand that. What can I do? What can I do, Sónya? cried Natásha with a happy yet frightened expression. But think what you are doing, cried Sónya. I can’t leave it like this. This secret correspondence... How could you let him go so far? she went on, with a horror and disgust she could hardly conceal. I told you that I have no will, Natásha replied. Why can’t you understand? I love him! Then I won’t let it come to that... I shall tell! cried Sónya, bursting into tears. What do you mean? For God’s sake... If you tell, you are my enemy! declared Natásha. You want me to be miserable, you want us to be separated.... When she saw Natásha’s fright, Sónya shed tears of shame and pity for her friend. But what has happened between you? she asked. What has he said to you? Why doesn’t he come to the house? Natásha did not answer her questions. For God’s sake, Sónya, don’t tell anyone, don’t torture me, Natásha entreated. Remember no one ought to interfere in such matters! I have confided in you.... But why this secrecy? Why doesn’t he come to the house? asked Sónya. Why doesn’t he openly ask for your hand? You know Prince Andrew gave you complete freedom—if it is really so; but I don’t believe it! Natásha, have you considered what these secret reasons can be? Natásha looked at Sónya with astonishment. Evidently this question presented itself to her mind for the first time and she did not know how to answer it. I don’t know what the reasons are. But there must be reasons! Sónya sighed and shook her head incredulously. If there were reasons... she began. But Natásha, guessing her doubts, interrupted her in alarm. Sónya, one can’t doubt him! One can’t, one can’t! Don’t you understand? she cried. Does he love you? Does he love me? Natásha repeated with a smile of pity at her friend’s lack of comprehension. Why, you have read his letter and you have seen him. But if he is dishonorable? He! dishonorable? If you only knew! exclaimed Natásha. If he is an honorable man he should either declare his intentions or cease seeing you; and if you won’t do this, I will. I will write to him, and I will tell Papa! said Sónya resolutely. But I can’t live without him! cried Natásha. Natásha, I don’t understand you. And what are you saying! Think of your father and of Nicholas. I don’t want anyone, I don’t love anyone but him. How dare you say he is dishonorable? Don’t you know that I love him? screamed Natásha. Go away, Sónya! I don’t want to quarrel with you, but go, for God’s sake go! You see how I am suffering! Natásha cried angrily, in a voice of despair and repressed irritation. Sónya burst into sobs and ran from the room.

Natásha went to the table and without a moment’s reflection wrote that answer to Princess Mary which she had been unable to write all the morning. In this letter she said briefly that all their misunderstandings were at an end; that availing herself of the magnanimity of Prince Andrew who when he went abroad had given her her freedom, she begged Princess Mary to forget everything and forgive her if she had been to blame toward her, but that she could not be his wife. At that moment this all seemed quite easy, simple, and clear to Natásha.

Oh, Sónya, if you knew him as I do! He said... He asked me what I had promised Bolkónski. He was glad I was free to refuse him. Sónya sighed sorrowfully. But you haven’t refused Bolkónski? said she. Perhaps I have. Perhaps all is over between me and Bolkónski. Why do you think so badly of me?

Sónya did not succumb to the tender tone Natásha used toward her. The more emotional and ingratiating the expression of Natásha’s face became, the more serious and stern grew Sónya’s.

Natásha, I am afraid for you! Afraid of what? I am afraid you’re going to your ruin, said Sónya resolutely, and was herself horrified at what she had said. Anger again showed in Natásha’s face. And I’ll go to my ruin, I will, as soon as possible! It’s not your business! It won’t be you, but I, who’ll suffer. Leave me alone, leave me alone! I hate you! Natásha! moaned Sónya, aghast. I hate you, I hate you! You’re my enemy forever! And Natásha ran out of the room.

Sonya and Natasha

Featured Characters: SONYA, NATASHA

[SONYA]
How was it I noticed nothing?
How could it go so far?
It can’t be that she loves him
It can’t be
Natasha

Natasha awakes and sees Sonya.

[NATASHA]
Sonya, you’re back
And with the tender resolve that often comes at the moment of awakening
I embraced my friend
But noticing Sonya’s look of embarrassment
My face expressed confusion
And suspicion
Sonya, you’ve read the letter?

[SONYA]
Yes

[NATASHA]
Oh Sonya, I’m glad
I can’t hide it any longer!
Now you know, we love one another!
Oh Sonya, he writes, he writes
He writes, he writes, he writes

[SONYA]
And Andrey?

[NATASHA]
Oh Sonya, if you only knew how happy I am!
You don’t know what love is

[SONYA]
But Natasha, can that all be over?

[NATASHA]
I do not grasp the question

[SONYA]
Are you refusing Prince Andrey?

[NATASHA]
Oh, you don’t understand anything!
Don’t talk nonsense, just listen

[SONYA]
But I can’t believe it, I don’t understand
How you loved one man a whole year
And suddenly—
You’ve only known him three days!
Natasha, you're joking!

[NATASHA]
Three days?
It seems to me I’ve loved him a hundred years
It seems to me I’ve never loved anyone before
Not like this
I have no will
My life is his
I’ll do anything he wants me to
What can I do?
Sonya, what can I do?

[NATASHA]
I’m so happy
And so frightened
Why can’t you understand?
I love him!

[SONYA]
Then I won’t let it come to that, I shall tell!
Bursting into tears

[NATASHA]
What do you mean?
For God’s sake, if you tell, you are my enemy!
You want me to be miserable
You want to tear us apart
For God’s sake, Sonya, don’t tell anyone, don’t torture me
I have confided in you

[SONYA]
What has happened between you?
What has he said to you?
Why doesn’t he come to the house and openly ask for your hand?
Why this secrecy?
Have you thought what his secret reasons may be?

[NATASHA]
I don’t know what the reasons are
But there must be reasons!
Sonya, one can’t doubt him!

[SONYA]
Does he love you?

[NATASHA]
Does he love me?
Why, you’ve read his letter, you’ve seen him
I can’t live without him

[SONYA]
Natasha, think of our family
And think of Prince Andrey

[NATASHA]
Andrey said I was free to refuse him

[SONYA]
But you haven’t refused him, or have you?

[NATASHA]
Perhaps I have
Perhaps all is over between me and Bolkonsky
Would you think so badly of me?

[SONYA]
I won’t succumb to your tender tone Natasha
I don’t trust him, Natasha!
I’m afraid for you, Natasha!
Afraid you are going to your ruin

[NATASHA]
Then I’ll go to my ruin, yes I will, as soon as possible!
But it’s not your business!
It won’t be you, it’ll be me, who’ll suffer
Leave me alone, yes leave me alone!
I hate you Sonya!
I hate you Sonya!
I hate you, I hate you!
You’re my enemy forever!

[SONYA]
I burst into sobs

Natasha runs out of the room.

[NATASHA]
And without a moment’s reflection
I wrote the answer to Princess Mary
I’d been unable to write all morning

[NATASHA]
All our misunderstandings are at an end
Forget everything and forgive me
But I can’t be Andrey’s wife